Inventory of the Patrick Henry Papers 1778-1927
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Patrick Henry Papers, 1778-1927, 1778-1792.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.2 H41
30 items.
Includes letters, 1778-1792, of Patrick Henry while living in Prince Edward County, Virginia and including letter, 28 May 1778, to Richard Henry Lee. Also includes copies of letters received by William Wirt from persons to whom he had written seeking biographical and anecdotal material concerning Henry (including one letter from George Wythe); prints and engravings of Henry; and an article concerning Patrick Henry's mother, Sarah Henry from the Journal of American History.
Patrick Henry,; Richard Henry Lee,; William Wirt,; George Wythe.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
29 items, in the possession of Swem Library before 1939.
Purchase: 1 item, 6/3/1980.
Biographical/Historical Information
Patrick Henry was born in Hanover County, Virginia in 1736. He was largely self-educated, becoming a prominent trial lawyer and great orator. The most famous phrase attributed to him is "Give me liberty or give me death." He was delegate to the House of Burgesses, 1765-1774; the Continential Congress, 1774-1776; and the Virginia provincial convention, 1775. He also served as governor of Virginia from 1776 to 1779 and from 1784 to 1786. Patrick Henry died in 1799.
Scope and Content Information
Includes letters, 1778-1792, of Patrick Henry while living in Prince Edward County, Virginia and including letter, 28 May 1778, to Richard Henry Lee. Also includes copies of letters received by William Wirt from persons to whom he had written seeking biographical and anecdotal material concerning Henry (including one letter from George Wythe); prints and engravings of Henry; and an article concerning Patrick Henry's mother, Sarah Henry from the Journal of American History.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection has been organized into four series. Series 1 contains portrait engravings and prints, Series 2 contains letters written to and from Patrick Henry, Series 3 contains photostatic copies of papers, and Series 4 contains material relating to Patrick Henry's mother, Sarah Henry.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Persons:
Henry, Patrick, 1736- 1799.; Henry, Sarah, 1784.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732- 1794.; Wirt, William, 1772- 1834.; Wythe, George, 1726-1806.
Subjects:
1778- 1927.
Contents List
  Series 1: Portrait Engravings and Prints
- Portrait engravings and prints., 13 items.
  Series 2: Letters to and from Patrick Henry
- Letters to and from Patrick Henry, 1778-1792.
  - P[atrick] Henry, W[illia]msburg,[Virginia], to R[ichard] H[enry] Lee, n.p., 28 May 1778., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Francis Watkins to Patrick Henry, 15 April 1790., 3 pages. ALS.
  - Col. Will[ia]m Fleming, Botetourt [County, Virginia], to Patrick Henry, Prince Edward [County, Virginia], 23[?] October 1790., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Will[ia]m Fleming, Botetourt [County, Virginia], to Col. Patrick Henry, Prince Edward [County, Virginia], 18 June 1791., 1 page. ALS.
  - P[atrick] Henry, P[rince] Edward [County, Virginia], to [?], 19 August 1792., 1 page. ALS.
    With a note included from T.S. Meade.
  - Jo[h]n Fontaine to Patrick Henry, n.d., 2 pages. ALS.
  Series 3: Photostatic Copies of Papers
- Photostatic copies of papers in the Library of Congress relating to Patrick Henry., 61 pages. 6 items.
- A letter regarding the Fontaine Ms. in the Cornell University Library, 19 January 1923., 1 page. TLS.
  Series 4: Material on Sarah Henry, Patrick Henry's Mother
- Material on Sarah Henry, Patrick Henry's mother.
  - "Patrick Henry's Mother," by Jean Cabell O'Neill. In the Journal of American History., 13 pages. PV.
  - Notes on Sarah Henry, mother of Patrick Henry, 3 items. 8 pages. ALS. 2 ph.
    With photographs of her tombstone and of the house in which she died.